this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
the radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome all to this episode of software
engineering radio today we welcome
Brandon Callum to the show to explore a
spec first model of API development
Brandon is the engineering manager for
the Pinterest developer platform team
Pinterest is a visual Discovery platform
and social commerce network with a
mission to inspire Brandon has also LED
other engineering teams at Pinterest
has a technology architect and
strategist Brandon specializes in
helping organizations scale to match
rapid growth welcome to the show Brenton
it's really great to have you here today
would you like to add anything else to
your bio before we get started no thank
you kanchan that was great and I'm very
excited to be here today to talk about
spec First Development so let's get into
it awesome just a couple of things
before we jump in I'd like to mention a
few related episodes we have done in the
past episode 387
on designing and testing apis
episode 383 Neil Madden on securing apis
and 376 Justin richer on API security
with or2 I'll put these links in the
show notes so Brendan what is the spec
first API approach how is it different
from API first maybe you could start
with explaining what is API first and
then explain what is spec first sure
yeah great yeah I see API first as sort
of a product strategy or philosophy and
spec first design or spec first code
generation as we'll get into as kind of
a practical or tactical way to put that
into practice
so if you've got alignment from your
product team which is not always easy to
get but if you do and you have
understanding that apis are a powerful
way to grow and scale your product then
the next thing that'll come to mind is
how do we actually make that happen how
do we ensure that the apis we deliver
and launch live up to our product goals
that they're consistent and high quality
and specfirst is is one way to organize
the process of development to ensure
those kinds of outcomes yeah so I can
talk a little bit more about how
specfirst works or some of the details
there absolutely so yeah getting into it
one level deeper when you think about
the different aspects of what an API is
one of the things that we often did in
the past is kind of start with the
business logic and work backwards from
there as to what the specification or
the interface should look like for
partners and when you do that you often
end up with an API that isn't consistent
with the rest of the endpoints that
you've already released that meets the
business goals internally but maybe
doesn't make sense externally and you've
already made decisions as to how the
wiring and the business logic should
work so you're kind of boxing yourself
in to what the interface should look
like spec first says no like first
things first is how is a client of the
API how is a consumer of the API going
to experience what you've built what is
their request going to need to look like
and what kind of response should they
expect and then everything internally
that happens from the business logic
perspective and on the back end is
secondary to that and that allows us to
answer questions like consistency and
standardization early in the process
rather than having to kind of at the
last minute figure that all out and
throw out a bunch of work so yeah would
you happen to have any example of being
not consistent before you started on
like first approach and what was the
issue yeah great question so a lot of
this was actually driven from partner
feedback too so this is not our first
current as we call it V5 of our public
API this is not our first attempt at
building external apis I've been at the
company for almost about eight years now
and I got to see you know some of the
first iterations of of our external apis
back in 2014 2015 and we've continued to
evolve and build and learn from our
partners and one of the biggest things
that different developers would tell us
is that they had a really hard time
predicting how the API would behave from
our documentation you know they'd read
the docs for one endpoint and they'd
test it out and it would tell a
completely different story you know and
likewise they learn how to use one set
of endpoints for one use use case say
campaign management and ads Analytics
and then they'd want to expand their
application to call some of our other
endpoints maybe around shopping and when
they would do that they'd see a
completely different design pattern a
different set of standards for how the
interface works sometimes even different
rate limiting mechanisms and so what
they're really asking for was
consistency predictability and not
having lots of kind of undocumented
changes that cause them to thrash and
break their apps yeah so we considered
All That feedback when we were launching
this new version of the API and we
decided that we really need to flip our
development process and we need to have
a consistent set of core reviewers who
look first at the spec design and the
quality of the interface that we're
presenting to Partners do the time stamp
Fields here and the the formatting of
this request match the kind of
conventions we've landed on for our
other apis so you know are we doing
request batching in the same way that we
are across these different endpoints and
things like that need to be front loaded
in the process makes sense a follow-up
question on that is so that did require
a change to the process as you mentioned
did that require other changes to the
team structures Arc structures any kind
of cultural changes we needed did you
have to overcome objections or any
hurdles yeah definitely definitely so I
alluded to this a little bit at the
beginning spec first is kind of a
tactical process for how to build an API
but you do really need product buy-in
and buy-in at different levels of the
company because not every team in
product use case depending on your
business and what your goals are not
every team might naturally think of an
external API component to how they build
their products and how they reach their
customers right so part of our team's
role is to even evangelize the potential
and the possibilities of working with
the API platform and it's really if we
go to those teams and we say you know
here's all this great stuff you can do
but there's this really lengthy
convoluted complex process you know for
building and iterating and getting stuff
out there we might get past the product
teams but the engineers are going to
look at that and and you know say well
we can't prioritize this or we don't
have the resources to do this so we knew
that part of enabling this change and
getting people to buy in API first was
making this process really easy right if
you follow the standard open API format
for defining your spec if you use the
linters and guidelines and
recommendations we have for how to build
and structure your endpoint then the
rest of this process will be really
quick and easy in terms of other process
changes I also mentioned earlier that we
wanted to have a core group of folks of
Engineers and some product folks and
Tech writers who could do a lot of the
spec review part right this is you know
similar to you know kind of generic code
review
but it's with a specific eye to
consistency across the whole spec so you
know you might have a product team who
owns like a shopping feature and they're
adding a new endpoint they're not
necessarily going to know everything
else about what's in the spec and what's
out there for partners right they might
follow your guidelines they might build
something you know pretty great but it
shouldn't be on them to read and
understand the entire product space
that's out there for partners to use so
one of the process changes we made was
to form this core review group rotating
review group to catch those kinds of
things and do a partner-centric like
consistency review of those spec changes
and because we're doing the spec changes
first you know and the spec is is
written in an open API you know yaml
format it's not quite the same as
reading complex business logic code or
back-end code we can have maybe a
broader audience of technical or
technical minded folks who can
contribute to that review group as well
and kind of spread the burden across a
larger group of folks so yeah that's it
Brendan did you encounter any cons so
this new approach any examples of
something that actually went wrong yeah
it's a great question of course we're
always you know as Engineers we're
always thinking about trade-offs and I
think it's not necessarily a con but
there's definitely a healthy tension
between maximum consistency across the
entire API Surface versus designing like
a single endpoint for a very specific
use case right if an engineer is given
the freedom to really only think about
that one narrow use case you know they
might choose to do things a little bit
differently versus having to slow down
and think about well yeah this might in
a vacuum this might be the perfect
option for this endpoint but we already
have 10 other endpoints that do
something similar so how can we meet in
the middle here with our approach right
so I wouldn't qualify that as a con
necessarily but it certainly adds a
little bit of time to the review process
to ensure that we have that consistency
I guess the the trade-off there is if
you don't do that and we kind of go back
to the model we had previously then it's
really a free-for-all and partners are
just left holding the bag right they're
the ones who have to figure out well
this specific API has this one very
Arcane way of doing things and this
other one is completely different and
some Partners will go along with that
Journey with you because the value is
there and the interest is there and the
will is there but if you really want to
scale and grow a sustainable ecosystem
that's not the right way to go about it
at least that's not what we think so
Pinterest actually had a specific spec
first launch I think you mentioned V5 of
the API what have you learned since the
launch both internally and internally
and how did this learning come about
sure yeah always important to take the
time to kind of be retrospective you
know as we continue on this Learning
Journey API development Journey we
launched V5 as you mentioned which is
the current available version if you go
to developers.penders.com and and look
at our API documentation we launched it
in a limited beta at the end of last
year 2021 and then kind of went
officially GA earlier this year in 2022.
it's already become our biggest API in
terms of number of daily active apps and
developers and you know we're also
looking at daily active users endpoint
usage and and kind of overall impact on
some of our business metrics and goals
and you know that's we think in no small
part due to the way we opened up the API
and allowed kind of any interested
developer to get started quickly and
easily and the benefits from the spec
first approach so I mentioned earlier
how one of the things Partners were
asking for is predictability well with
the spec first approach we're able to
deliver just that right because the spec
is the source of Truth and we generate
our Handler code our server code based
on that spec what Partners see in our
documentation is it's the same code that
our API server is using to validate and
parse quests so there's no more kind of
guessing and wandering around in the
dark hoping you've you've got the right
request format
on the flip side some of our previous
existing Partners who had already
invested a lot of time and energy to
understand our you know previous
versions of the API with all of its
eccentricities you know they now have a
potential migration at hand and we hope
there's a clear incentive for them to do
that with the new version and all the
new development that's happening we also
just launched an API sandbox and our
first ever Pinterest official sdks and
client code so we're hoping to
incentivize all those existing Partners
to move to the new version could you
talk about some internal learnings as
well yeah sure sure one thing that we've
we've really observed from launching
this new API and now having a bunch of
different product teams across the
company build endpoints and and work
with our platform wikis docs written
best practices are great but like IDE
tools validation rules linters are even
better right so bringing the best
practice is and the guidance into real
concrete actionable rules for developers
so and also bringing it right to where
they're actually doing the development
work has been huge so you know for
example one of the tools we use a lot in
API development is vs code there's a
number of plugins and things that can
assist with open API development and
working with spec files in that tool and
we also use a linter tool an open source
linter called spectral to to write those
rules and help validate the specs so
those have been really important for
helping people learn and and guiding
them on the right path so that when it
comes time for code review or not going
back and throwing out everything they've
they've written and asking them to start
over so do you have any other feedback
from partners that you'd like to share
yeah yeah this is less feedback and and
more just another observation of kind of
so we talked a lot about the technical
changes one of the the new things with
V5 was actually opening up signups to to
anyone right
obviously you've got to have a Pinterest
account and register on the site to use
the API but our previous like external
apis were very invite only kind of white
glove service and we weren't really sure
we could scale them and open them up to
a wider audience without lots of
challenges so D5 was built with that
scale in mind one thing that we've we're
consistently you know learning and
relearning is that you can never really
lower that barrier to entry enough for
for folks who are maybe maybe developing
their first API app right so you know
our previous set of developers and our
audience maybe we could take some
concepts for granted like hey everyone
knows how oauth 2.0 Works in general
right which you know if you've ever
worked with oau 2.0 uh it's a lot right
and so we're consistently trying to add
different kinds of docs tutorials code
samples we even had a teammate write a
interactive tutorial on glitch I don't
know if you've ever messed around with
that
it's kind of a way to put up different
code and apps and let people remix them
and see all the source code and that's
gotten a lot of great reviews from
Partners who are you know maybe learning
oauth for the first time so offering
different kinds of resources for for
folks who have different levels of
technical background and experience
working with apis is a great way to get
to just broaden your audience and get
more folks involved it's a lot of very
very useful information there Brenton
how do you actually get this feedback do
you reach out to the partners do they
reach out to you do you have a process
yeah that's another great question right
like you launch this API you invite
people to sign up you've got some
metrics internally but how do you get
that qualitative feedback from from
Partners who are that's so valuable
right like I think as a as an API
developer you might not necessarily have
the same signal that you get from
someone using a web tool or a mobile app
right and so figuring out what was the
experience for the developer as they
were learning your API as they were
testing things what does the raw set of
request logs and traffic that you have
internally not show or or cover right so
it is really important to think about
how you can capture that one of the
things we've done really well since
launching is for each kind of new
iteration or feature for the API we will
try to do it in a limited beta fashion
first and so we'll open it up for
interest and we'll also proactively
reach out to some of our partners who
who have registered or shown interests
in the past get a you know small and but
large enough group but still manageable
to kind of come on board with testing it
and get early access to the feature and
then you know they have a more direct
connection with our product team and our
program managers throughout the life of
that beta and we can get that valuable
feedback directly and we also encourage
as much as possible we encourage our
product engineering teams to sit in on
those sessions right you know we don't
as a developer platform team we don't
know necessarily want to be the
bottleneck or the single conduit for all
all developer feedback to come into the
company like it's great when the
shopping teams and the monetization
teams and the other teams across the
company can sit down and hear it
firsthand how developers are using their
endpoints and their products we also
just recently started a developer
community so that's a place where folks
can go and start asking questions we're
in there looking at questions but also
we hope to grow that Community more so
that developers can share experience and
best practices and things with each
other and it's not just a a one-way you
know street from from Pinterest down and
of course we rely on a really great
customer success and support team that's
answering kind of like reactive problems
questions issues that come in through
our help center and other social
channels so certainly seems like a lot
of learnings what still keeps you up at
night yeah yeah good question yeah yeah
I think we I mean it's a good problem to
have but with success with lots of new
developers with lots of new endpoints
and use cases coming online to to the
API you know there's a challenge of of
scale and complexity right we made a
decision when we launched V5 that we
wanted to make one consistent API that
covers pretty much all of the different
things you can do with Pinterest from
boards and pins to analytics to campaign
management to shopping and I think
that's that's really paid off for us
because partners are able to pick and
choose the things they want to do and
add and adjust really easily if these
aren't separate siled apis for them to
use each new endpoint each new use case
you know adds to the overall complexity
of the system and the API and you know
how do we continue to keep it simple
keep it consistent as we add more and
more things that's why one of the things
that I'm always trying to think about
and stay ahead of let's not get into
some of the details of the design so the
launch announcement indicated that not
only every change but every bug fix and
of course every feature really starts by
considering the impact to the public
spec do you have an example that we can
use to walk through and see how the spec
was impacted yeah sure sure yeah that's
right it is really a commitment across
the engineering development process
so one of the things I think that's
critical to Pinterest is and amazing
about Pinterest is that a pin can really
be anything right it could be a recipe
that you've saved that you want to cook
tonight it can be a travel destination
or a new jacket or a hat that you think
you want to check out or maybe add to
your your wardrobe and so with all those
different kinds of data comes you know a
really complex backend schema or
structure for the kinds of data we store
for each pin on the platform now think
about trying to Simply and consistently
and succinctly represent what that pin
could be to an external partner through
an API right they don't have all the
context on the different Data Systems
that store all of that information where
the images are coming from you know how
many images or videos are associated
with each pin and so one of the things
that the spec first process allowed to
really clean up and produce a higher
quality quality like experiences around
creative formats for Pins so whether
it's a single image or a product pin or
a video pin when we sat down and looked
at what a pin should be in the spec
first what the request and response
should look like it allowed us to build
a model that separates some of the
common schema and shared attributes that
go across all pins on Pinterest so
something like a link a description a
title and then tie that with a more
flexible media object where we could
swap in and out using open API
discriminators different schemas to
associate with that so now we've got
something that is consistent but is also
flexible allows us to introduce new
creative formats so you know as those
product teams experiment and try out new
things we can introduce them to Partners
and say hey guess what there's a new PIN
format all of the same fields that you
you know and love will be there but this
one is going to have some extra stuff
and you can identify it using this the
same media type discriminator so that's
that's one example I think on the the
other side once you've created some pins
once you've messed around with different
parts of the API one of the first things
that that Partners want to then be able
to do is get analytics about how is my
pin performing is it getting seen by
pinners across the platform you know
what are the Impressions look like what
are the clicks look like right and
different product segments and use cases
within Pinterest produce different kinds
of metrics and analytics for the for
those different things right a video pin
is going gonna have different metrics
than a Shopping product pin than just a
simple image pin right and so starting
from the spec again allowed us to
identify like a common analytics
framework that we could share across all
of those use cases you know where was
the overlap between product and
advertising and where is the overlap
between video and non-video and are the
metric names the same are they slightly
different can we get those teams to
agree on a similar metric name or can we
just obfuscate that complexity for
partners and maybe simplify it in the
API so metrics is definitely another
area where we were able to make things a
lot more consistent with any differences
in designing the API for different
personas so I understand there are
creators
then there's the business users and then
the pinners themselves for sure yeah
that's a great question yeah you know we
spend a lot of time thinking about those
different personas across the product
and their goals when they come to
Pinterest are are different right a
Pinner is is coming to the platform to
be inspired to get inspiration to find a
recipe for you know what they're going
to cook that night or to plan their next
travel or redesign their their room and
creators and businesses are coming to
connect with those printers right to
share their unique products their
perspective their knowledge their
creativity and help Inspire those people
right so they are truly like partners
with us in that mission and so you know
when we sat down and looked at the kind
of Matrix of use cases and the different
views across the Pinner consumer
audience and the business or Creator or
Advertiser audience you know we
identified a couple of things where
there was like overlap and and that
became kind of the initial foundation of
the API the the building blocks for the
CPI so boards and pins are are really
the building blocks of the platform and
they're a centerpiece of our API as well
whatever you're building whatever the
use case is you're probably going to
start with those endpoints right so we
know that that's a common entry point
for the API and we knew we needed to
invest a lot of time in getting that
design right and making it future proof
and flexible and from there once you've
got your boards and your pins organized
and and you're allowing pinners to save
stuff and you're allowing businesses to
publish new things and reach new
audiences you can build on that and get
into advertising or shopping or
analytics and so I think it was
identifying that overlap area and then
filling out from there so for the
approval process you mentioned reviewers
to you envision challenges and scaling
this process yeah well you know we have
had a lot of experience now with scale
since since first launching the API the
developer platform form team were the
ones kind of bringing this idea to the
Forefront initially and so we took it on
ourselves to do some of the design work
and development work up front to kind of
demonstrate to the rest of the
engineering team this is what the gold
standard or canonical standard for what
we think this API can be and what it can
do but since then 90 plus of the
development work that's happened in the
spec and in the API has come from other
teams right so we've really shifted from
kind of the initial development
Innovation phase to now being
Consultants being reviewers offering
guidance and enabling those other teams
to be successful in the platform that
makes sense earlier you had mentioned
challenges of or at least the need to
educate your partners on migration and
the benefits of doing that so where are
you at now with deprecating older
versions yeah that's a great question so
with the history of the of the company
and the product and in our previous
version versions you know we really made
some great Partnerships and have
partners that have invested time and
effort in building to previous versions
of the apis and they've they've gotten
value from those apis and they've you
know they've helped Inspire pinners with
the content they've created and all the
great things they've brought to our
platform so you know it's important for
us to respect that to appreciate that
and to make it as easy as possible for
for those Partners to move
so the first step we knew is hey this
new API it can be different it can be
consistent we can take some some big
risks and some moves away from things
we've done in the past
but we know that we have to be able to
offer parity in terms of features in
terms of products with what our partners
are used to previously so we knew we had
a couple different product areas we had
to cover and support before we could
really start beating the drum of for
migration right it's never too early to
let your partners know what you're
planning and thinking they really
appreciate it just like us they've got
development timelines and trade-offs
they're thinking about and making and
they're probably integrating to other
kinds of platforms and so you know
they're thinking about the work that it
will take to migrate your API as well as
other apis and other other challenges
they're dealing with so giving them lots
of heads up and advanced notice is also
really helpful and then when it comes
down to it one of the things we try to
do is and we've got a number of these
now on the site is provide migration
guides so calling out specific
differences calling out some of the
biggest changes and then getting into
the details sometimes endpoint by
endpoint talking about what's different
there's a hunger to see that level of
detail before Partners can really
estimate okay how much effort is it
going to take me to move to this new
version of the API you know that's the
first question you get is well what
what's actually different what's changed
right and yeah so we've reached that
parity Milestone so we are now able to
offer on D5 a wide range of of things
that our previous siled apis had all in
one place and so now we're letting folks
know that it's time to move and giving
them you know the resources the docs and
the tools they need to do that so that's
kind of where we're at thank you for
that Brendan I'd like to now explore
some related API topics so we can spend
a few minutes on that
open API tooling certainly seems like at
the core of your practical approach you
did mention some other tooling as well
but initially as you were evaluating
open API tooling was anything else that
you evaluated yeah great question yeah
so launching this new API was a chance
to really take stock of you know what
our partners have been asking for and
what the options are and kind of where
this the API development world is
heading so of course we looked at some
other things like graphql but coming
back and grounding ourselves in kind of
that partner feedback and experience we
continue to see you know restful apis
and open API as a common denominator and
kind of our highest priority interface
to build that doesn't rule out possible
graphql supports it's definitely
something we're supporting internally
for some of our own native clients on
other apis but it for thinking partner
first and and what they're asking for or
the restful framework seemed like the
right choice and once you kind of make
narrow down that decision you know open
API is a truly open source and open
framework that has a ton of tooling a
ton of support a ton of documentation so
it was kind of a no-brainer to go into
that from there ignition graphql is that
something used for internal apis maybe
let me just step back and ask this about
internal apis the announcement really
focused on public facing apis does it
cover internal apis yeah yeah yeah good
point give some context there so this
API that we're offering is built first
and foremost for external Partners right
that is our audience that is who we're
looking at that is the audience that is
guiding all of our design choices and
our approach of course balancing that
with security privacy and you know are
the apis we're offering going to
actually help people get inspired and
you know Drive our business goals but
internally obviously we've we've got a
different landscape and ecosystem and so
you know graphql is is something we've
we've been exploring and we'll continue
to to work on internally so you know for
things like the Pinterest web app and
Pinterest IOS and Android apps what
we've seen is you know a continued
desire to iterate rapidly to launch lots
of different experiments as we do on the
platform to you know improve our printer
experience and to be able to craft you
know more complex joins and queries
across different kinds of data to power
those experiences so that are some of
the factors driving the graphql stuff
internally but for partners externally
it's it's kind of a lower priority at
the moment so maybe let's take a segue a
little bit the stocking in general about
your internal apis that you use to
support your different clients the
browser-based mobile clients do you feel
any challenges and reusing some of those
apis maybe in terms of you know
chattedness how much data is exchanged
any general guidelines or experiences in
that area sure certainly yeah at a lower
level with the V5 API and what we're
offering to Partners there is a level of
shared framework code across internal
and external and so it's not a clean
break but in terms of the representation
in terms of the specification the
interface it is quite different right
and it is a restful API right where as
internally we're exploring both we have
both rest and graphql options for
internal clients in terms of like
chattiness as you said and network
traffic we've done you know a fair
amount of work to think about how these
different clients request data from the
apis how they can even through rest you
know enable certain kinds of joining
techniques so you know are you looking
for perhaps a board and a set of pins on
those boards and all the users that are
associated with those pins right if we
know that the client needs needs that
join data up front then yeah how can we
craft the right interface and requests
to provide that without lots of requests
going back and forth definitely an area
we've spent a lot of time like
optimizing and building on for our
internal apis and yeah something that
you know graphql kind of offers a
different approach to right than a set
of rest endpoints how do you do this do
you have kpis and how do you measure
performance yeah so kpis always lots of
kpis lots of metrics you know I think we
can kind of break them into different
categories one is all about performance
stability kind of nuts and bolts of how
the service the health of the service is
doing latency request sizes things like
that rate limiting and then of course
there's measuring the actual business
impact of of the apis right we launched
an API for conversions recently which
allows advertisers to to have a secure
way to send us conversion data for you
know all of the checkouts and
transactions that are happening on their
site and so you know one of the things
we need to be able to measure is is that
actually helping those advertisers get
Roi from our advertising product is it
actually driving adoption in the way
that we want it to so for those things
you know we might have a much more
standard set of metrics to measure
across the API for kind of performance
and reliability but for each product use
case it is a bit of a partnership to
work with those teams to understand okay
when somebody uses is one of these
endpoints what's the downstream impact
right is it kicking off some jobs down
the line later do we need to measure
adoption engagement after the fact for
two weeks later to really truly see the
impact or is it more direct right is
there direct Revenue number that we can
tie back to say the budget of a campaign
that was that was created through the
API so that's something that I think we
try to call out early when teams come to
us to want to build in the API we ask
them you know what does success look
like for you with with launching this
this API and if we know we're going to
need to capture some new types of
metrics or join some different data
together you know we call that out early
so we can be ready to to start measuring
it when we launch wanted to now focus a
little bit on your team structures and
devops processes as well and with any
emphasis on changes that have happened
due to the spec first approach so my
first question is that the announcement
mentioned and I believe you mentioned
too that different endpoints are owned
by different product teams
and to these teams choose their own
stack stack for the API implementation
yeah yeah so yes and no all right so we
offer an API Gateway and a spec service
and and request validation and kind of
response handling so you know kind of
the core of the API layer as a service
to them and you know that includes rate
limiting authentication authorization
and then what the API actually does the
business Logic the meat of it is up to
them there are some standard options you
know a lot of use cases share like a
common backend system and so sometimes
you know if a product team is is adding
something in an existing use case or
space that decision will sort of already
be made for them but sometimes you know
in the course of building a new endpoint
there's the spec design part and then
okay this is the first time the API
service is talking to this system what
do we need to figure out you know are
there region changes we need to think
about are there new types of rate
limiting capacity changes we need to
think about what's a traffic pattern for
this endpoint going to look like versus
kind of the rest of the API so you know
we try to offer a template but there is
a fair amount of flexibility for how
those product teams connect the API
layer to whatever action systems they
have so your role is higher if when it's
the first time and then later on this
more delegated to the team itself even
related designing the apis is that fair
yeah I think that's generally right I
think if we're a small team right we own
the shared resources and the overall
developer experience but having a single
API team build every possible API use
case with the amount of stuff we're
trying to do and the range of things you
can do with Pinterest just doesn't seem
like the right way to scale right so we
offer the API expertise and the guidance
and overall kind of stewardship of the
service but we really want to get the
different product teams engaged involved
ramped up on what a good endpoint looks
like and then eventually you know when
they build those endpoints they're
identified as the owner for those
endpoints so that means things like
traffic alerts or success rate alerts or
other things can get routed to their
team automatically right so that if it
is a back-end specific or product
specific problem they can look at it and
deal with it versus something related to
the overall framework I think what we
found is that naturally there are
different people across these different
teams who are really excited about
working with apis and working with
partners and so we've kind of built you
know initially informal and now starting
to be more formalized kind of group of
stakeholders hi stakeholders who you
know are not just thinking about their
specific use case in their endpoint but
how to make the product better overall
and we welcome that kind of feedback and
we involve them in our planning
discussions like we're doing right now
for 2023 planning and we think that's a
great way to kind of build and maintain
those relationships and connections with
other product teams so that we can make
sure that the service does what they
need to do if it's a great API for
partners but no product teams internally
want to to build new features for it
that doesn't leave us in a good place so
so not directly related to apis though
but these teams product teams do they
own a complete vertical slice meaning
you know do they have ux designers and
ux developers as well on the team yeah
good question yeah I would say for the
most part yes right so oftentimes they
will have some full stack developers who
are kind of launching a new feature
across for example our ads manager web
UI right and our external V5 API right
so they're launching a new campaign
objective or a new type of creative
format in the API and in one of our
native interfaces or tools and so
naturally like the first kinds of
questions developers have are what is
the native product experience for this
feature right I'm interacting it as a
developer through the API but what does
it actually look like when it gets onto
Pinterest right can I see an example of
that can I play around with it on
Pinterest can I test it first before I
build my integration right so we try to
get involved early in that process and
identify that kind of information with
those product teams and so you know we
don't just want them to produce a spec
for us to review you know we want to
understand a little bit about what the
product is what it's going to look like
what the design what the ux is going to
look like and so that's a really fun
part of the job companies getting to be
really Broad and seeing across all these
different teams and use cases so who has
a responsibility for testing so unit
testing integration testing across
different endpoints maybe performance
maybe security testing yeah I mean we're
all responsible all Engineers here at
Pinterest you know were responsible for
things that we're putting out for
pinners to think about privacy to think
about security you know I think one
advantage of having kind of separation
between our external and internal
systems is being able to make different
decisions about how authentication works
right you know a token for the external
API does or doesn't have to work for an
internal API or vice versa right in
terms of testing you know we do ask our
engineers in general and our product
teams to take a lot of responsibility
with that right so when they're coming
to us with new endpoints and new aspect
changes the responsibility first lies
with them to also provide those unit
tests and also update our integration
tests framework we are lucky enough to
have you know some QA support as well so
you know some folks that are really
experienced and just breaking apis and
testing all kinds of different edge
cases and use cases so we try to provide
that extra layer of coverage we set the
expectation up front that you know you
own the spec you own the business logic
and you're also going to update unit
tests and integration tests with with
changes that you're making makes sense
let's talk a little bit about hiring and
onboarding what do you look for when
hiring developers at Pinterest yeah
that's a good question I mean I'll
selfishly talk about what I look for on
on our team but I think I can
extrapolate that a little bit more
generally too I think the unique
Challenge and fun of working on a
developer platform team is getting to
work with developers around the world
right they're constantly surprising us
with the ideas and The Innovation and
the different kinds of things that they
build on top of our Ai and that can be
really fun but it can also be
challenging because no day is the same
right every day you're seeing something
kind of new and so I think there's a
certain type of you know engineer that
really leans into into that variety and
different type of challenge every day
versus maybe sometimes and I think we've
all had these different phases in our
careers but sometimes maybe you just
really want to go deep in a specific
subject area and you know focus on
optimizing or making a certain process
or thing more efficient that's not
really what our focus is day to day so
we're looking for developers and
Engineers who can have a broad range of
experience and knowledge and are open to
and interested in learning about new
things new systems new languages and
working with lots of different product
teams internally we obviously appreciate
folks that have prior open API
experience and can kind of kind of you
know talk to different trade-offs and
opinions about how to design an endpoint
and what makes a good endpoint but we
also work with folks who come to us from
other disciplines and just want to learn
and grow and so you know that's one of
my favorite things to do is is to help
grow those folks and and Mentor them and
get them experience with the platform so
thanks Brendan that's quite useful
trying to start to wrap up now
with all the talk we've had on apis
what do you say to people that might
still be scraping on Pinterest
no comment no I mean if you're
interested in the data that we have at
Pinterest and as a developer I think why
wouldn't you be right we've got this
amazing web of of connected nodes
between boards and pins and and folks
that are creating content if you're
interested in in helping your customers
your users or building an app for people
that that can help them get inspired to
help them do real things in their life
and go plan that trip that they've
really been been dying to do then you
know these apis are made for you and we
invite you to come sign up and try them
out and give us the feedback you know
we're here we're a real team of people
we're interested and we're passionate
about what we think Pinterest can offer
and yeah and you know so sign up and
give it a shot anything that we missed
that you'd like to cover today no this
is a lot of fun thank you for having me
kanchan so Brendan how can people follow
you or contact you yeah I invite
everyone to join at
developers.penders.com go there check
out our docs register for an app and
we'll take a look and get you into the
program we also have our spec published
to GitHub so if you check out github.com
Pinterest there is a number of public
tools and repos like a quick start guide
and our first ever client code which is
python API client so yeah check out
developers.pinterest.com and our public
GitHub presence as well that's good we
can put those links in the show notes
thank you so much Brendan this was very
very interesting really really happy to
have you on this show today thank you
likewise
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening